<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="montaigne.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Montaigne, "To the Reader"</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From 1588 edition, with marginal notes</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>         
         <div type="preface">
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <p>You have here, Reader, a book whose faith can be trusted, a book which warns you from
               the start that I have set myself no other end but a private family one. I have not
               been concerned to serve you nor my reputation: my powers are inadequate for such a
               design. I have dedicated this book to the private benefit of my friends and kinsmen
               so that, having lost me (as they must do soon) they can find here again some traits
               of my character and of my humours. They will thus keep their knowledge of me more
               full, more alive. If my design had been to seek the favour of the world I would have
                  <ref target="#n1"><seg source="bordeaux_copy">decked myself out better and
                     presented myself in a studied gait</seg></ref><note xml:id="n1">The sections
                  highlighted in another color indicate text that Montaigne added into the margins
                  of his copy of the 1588 edition. This annotated copy is known as the Bordeaux
                  copy.</note>. Here I want to be seen in my simple, natural, everyday fashion,
               without striving or artifice: for <choice>
                  <orig>c'est moi que je peins</orig>
                  <reg>it is my own self that I am painting</reg>
               </choice>. Here, drawn from life, you will read of my defects and my native form so
               far as respect for social convention allows: for had I found myself among those
               peoples who are said still to live under the sweet liberty of Nature’s primal laws, I
               can assure you that I would most willingly have portrayed myself whole, and wholly
               naked. </p>
            <p> And therefore, Reader, I myself am the subject of my book: it is not reasonable that
               you should employ your leisure on a topic so frivolous and so vain.</p>
            <signed>Therefore, Farewell: From Montaigne; <ref target="#n2"><date><seg
                        source="bordeaux_copy">this first of March, One thousand, five hundred and
                        eighty</seg></date></ref><note xml:id="n2">In the 1588 edition, Montaigne's
                  publisher had updated the original 1580 date to reflect the release of the new
                  edition, and no doubt to mark the beginning of the term covered by publisher's new
                  7-year privilege. In his corrections, Montaigne reverted back to the original date
                  from the first edition.</note>.</signed>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>

         <figure>
            <figDesc>Portrait of Montaigne</figDesc>
            <graphic
               url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/8b/Montaigne_1584_-_Martellange.jpg"
            />
         </figure>

         <div type="chapter" n="18">
            <head>On Giving the Lie</head>
            <p>Yes. But somebody will tell me that my project of using myself as a subject to write
               about would be pardonable in exceptional, famous men who by their reputations had
               given us the desire to know them. That is certainly true: I admit it; I am aware that
               a mere craftsman will scarcely glance up from his work to look at a man of the common
               mould, whereas shops and work-places are emptied to look at a great and famous
               personality arriving in town. It is unseemly for anyone to make himself known except
               he who can provide some example and whose life and opinions can serve as a model.
               Caesar and Xenophon could firmly base their narrations on the greatness of their
               achivements which formed a just and solid foundation. So we can regret the loss of
               the diaries of Alexander the Great and of the commentaries on their own actions which
               Augusuts, <seg source="bordeaux_copy">Cato,</seg> Syll, Brutus and others left behind
               them. We love to study the faces of such men even in bronze and stone.</p>
            <p>That rebuke is very true: but it hardly touches on me:</p>

            <cit>
               <quote xml:lang="la">Non recito cuiquam, nisi amicis, idque rogatus, <lb/>Non ubivis,
                  coramve quibuslibet. In medio qui <lb/>Scripto foro recitent, sunt multi, quique
                  lavantes.</quote>

               <quote xml:lang="en">I do not read this to anyone except my friends; even then they
                  have to ask me; I do not do so anywhere or to anyone. Some men read their works to
                  the public in the Forum or in the baths!</quote>
            </cit>

            <p>I am not preparing a statue to erect at a city crossorads nor in a Church or some
               other public place:</p>

            <cit>
               <quote xml:lang="la">Non equidem hoc studeo, bullatis ut mihi musis <lb/>Pagina turgescat.
                  <lb/>Secreti loquimur.</quote>

               <quote xml:lang="en">I do not intend to puff up my pages with inflated trifles: we
                  are talking in private.</quote>
            </cit>

            <p>It is <seg source="bordeaux_copy">for some corder of a library and as a pastime</seg>
               for a neighbour, a relative or a friend who will find pleasure in meeting me and
               frequenting me again through this portrait. Those others took heart to speak of
               themselves because they found their subject rich and worthwhile: I on the contrary
               because I find it so sterile and meagre that no suspicion of ostentation can fall
               upon me.</p>

            <p>However, if my own descendants have different tastes, I shall have the means of
               giving as good as I get, since when that time comes they cannot possibly have less
               concern of me than I will for them! The only commerce I have with the public at large
               is my borrowing their printing-tools, which are more ready and convenient. In
               exchange <ref target="#n3"><seg source="bordeaux_copy">I may provide wrapping-paper
                     to stop some slab of butter from melting in the market</seg></ref><note
                  xml:id="n3">Note the intensified irony in Montaigne's 1588 editions</note>:</p>
            <cit>
               <quote xml:lang="la">Ne toga cordyllis, ne penula desit olivis;</quote>

               <quote xml:lang="en">Lest they are short of wrappings for their tunny-fish or their
                  olives;</quote>
            </cit>

            <cit>
               <quote xml:lang="la">Et laxas scombris saepe dabo tunicas.</quote>

               <quote xml:lang="en">And I shall often provide a loose garment to wrap up their
                  mackerel.</quote>
            </cit>

            <p><seg source="bordeaux_copy">Even if nobody reads me, have I wasted my time when I
                  have entertained myself during so many idle hours with thoughts so useful and
                  agreable?</seg></p>
         </div>



         <div type="chapter" n="19">
            <head>On Freedom of Conscience</head>

            <p>It is quite normal to see good intentions, when not carried out with moderation,
               urging men to actions which are truly vicious. In the present quarrel which is
               driving France to distraction with its <ref target="#n4">civil wars</ref><note
                  xml:id="n4">Montaigne is referring to the Religious Wars, a series of nine wars
                  between Protestant and Catholic parties, which tore France apart between 1561 and
                  1594.</note>, the better and more wholesome party is certainly the one upholding
               the religion and constitution of our country. Now among the men of honour who support
               it (for I am not talking about people who use it as a pretext for settling private
               scores, satisfying their greed or courting the favour of princes but about those who
               support it out of true zeal for their religion and a secred desire to defend the
               peace and good estate of their homeland) even among such men as those you can find
               many who, once passion drives them beyond the bounds of reason, take decisions which
               are unjust, violent and rash.</p>
            <p>It is certain that, in those early days when our religion begin to be becaked by the
               authority of law, zeal provided many with weapons to use against all sorts of pagan
               books, causing the learned public to suffer staggering losses. I reckon that this
               inordinate zeal caused more harm to literature than all the fires started by the
               Barbarians.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
